Guide to the Douglas Moore Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Douglas Moore Papers,
1907-1963
Moore, Douglas, 1893-1969.
21 linear ft. (ca. 6,200 items in 45 boxes and 1 flat box)
Columbia University, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, N.Y. 10027.
4079541
Biographical Note
Composer, who was also professor of music at Columbia University from 1926-1962.
Scope and Content
Professional and personal correspondence and original scores and sketches. In addition to the numerous original compositions, there are letters and related materials dealing with these works. These include production notes, librettos and data concerning the production and performances of such works as: "The Ballad of Baby Doe," "The Devil and Daniel Webster," "Giants in the Earth," and "White Wings." There is material relating to the curriculum and administration of Columbia's Music Department, of which Moore was chairman since 1926. His correspondence related to his membership of the Century Club, the McDowell Association, and the National Institute of Arts and Letters, and correspondence concerning his editorship of the Prentice Hall Music Series is also included. Of interest are several dozen printed scores and a few books written, inscribed, and signed by fellow composers such as Ernest Bloch, Vincent D'Indy, and Roger Sessions
1991 Addition: Correspondence with some related photographs and clippings. The majority of the letters are by Douglas Stuart Moore to his mother, Myra D. Moore. This correspondence, which spanned a 27 year period from the fall of 1906 to late 1933 represents perhaps the most comprehensive record of Moore's life, for it was his habit to write to his mother every Sunday, a ritual to which he was remarkably faithful. The various stages of Moore's life are apparent in his letters: his first experience away from home at the Hotchkiss School in Connecticut, his undergraduate years at Yale, time spent in a Maritime Academy in Maryland, his service in the Navy during the First World War, his tenure as Musical Director of the Cleveland Museum of Art, further travels in Europe, his position in the Music Department of Columbia University (1926-1962). The letters also follow the course of Myra Moore's life, where she lived in Brooklyn, Long Island, and finally Orange County California. There are some letters from other members of the family to Myra Moore. A few remaining letters that are not addressed to Moore's mother, are letters he wrote to other members of his family.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Columbia Course Material
Series IV: Scores
Series V: Manuscripts Scores and Sketches in Moore's Hand
Series VI: Oversize Material
Subjects
Columbia University.--Music dept.; Sessions, Roger, 1896-1985.; Music--Manuscripts.; Composition (Music); Lectures.; Librettos.; Minutes.; Motion pictures.; Portraits.; Sketches.; Scores.; Sheet music.; Surveys.; College teachers.; Composers.; Musicians.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
Papers Moore, Mrs. Douglas and family, etc. Gift
03/07/91 M-07-03-91 1991 Addition
Gift of Mrs Douglas Moore & family, 1971 & 1973.
Gift of Mrs Bradford Kelleher & Miss Sarah Moore, 1980, 1987 & 1991.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Adler, Kurt Herbert To Douglas Moore, San Francisco, 2 May 1960, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Barlow, Wayne (Box 1)
  - Bacon, Ernst (Box 1)
  - Belmont, Eleanor Robson (Box 1)
  - Benet, William Rose (Box 1)
  - Bing, Rudolph (Box 1)
  - Borge, Victor (Box 1)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck (Box 1)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray (Box 1)
  - Cleland, Thomas Maitland (Box 1)
  - Copland, Aaron (Box 1)
  - Damrosch, Walter (Box 1)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David (Box 1)
  - Fekete, Zolton (Box 1)
  - Foss, Lukas (Box 1)
  - Glanville-Hicks, Peggy (Box 1)
  - Goossens, Eugene (Box 1)
  - Graham, Martha (Box 1)
  - Hanson, Howard (Box 1)
  - Hartford, Huntington (Box 1)
  - Langstaff, John Meredith (Box 1)
  - MacDowell, Marian Nevins (Mrs. Edward) (Box 1)
  - MacLeish, Archibald (Box 1)
  - Mannes, Leopold (Box 1)
  - Mason, Daniel Gregory (Box 1)
  - Mason, Gregory (Box 1)
  - Menuhin, Yehudi (Box 1)
  - Meyerowitz, Jan (Box 1)
  - Mitropoulos, Dimitri (Box 1)
  - Partch, Harry (Box 1)
  - Rodzinski, Artur (Box 1)
  - Rudel, Julius (Box 1)
  - Schoenberg, Arnold (Box 1)
  - Schuman, William (Box 1)
  - Sessions, Roger Huntington (Box 1)
  - Szigeti, Joseph (Box 1)
  - Weisgall, Hugo (Box 1)
  - Moore, Douglas Stuart To Myra D. Moore (Box 2 - 9)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  - Moore Family Correspondence, 1904 - 1948 (Box 10)
  - Adam was my Grandfather (Box 11)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1949-1960 (Box 11)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters Minutes (Box 11)
  - American Society of Composers and Publishers (A.S.C.A.P.) (Box 11)
  - Ballad of Baby Doe -- Central City -- General Correspondence (Folders 1-1.) -- M.S. and I.S. Iscaas, Lucy Kroll, Michael Myerberg et. al. 1-3 (Box 11)
  - Ballade Of William Sycamore (Box 11)
  - Biographical Material - with Portraits (Box 11)
  - Carry Nation (Box 12)
  - Century Association (Box 12)
  - Clarinet Quintet (Box 12)
  - Columbia University Extension -- Humanities -- Music -- Department Budget (Folders 1-2) -- Music Department Curriculum -- Music Department Reports (Box 12)
  - Composers Survey - American Music Center (Box 12)
  - Correspondence Referring To More Than One Work, 1928 - 1936; 1941- 1944; 1945; 1946; 1947; 1948; 1949; 1950 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, January 1951 - April 1951; May 1951 - August 1951; September 1951 - December 1951; 1952; 1953; 1956; 1957 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1958; 1959; 1960 (2 Folders); 1961; 1962; 1963 (Box 15)
  - Cotollion -- Dedication -- Destroyer Life -- Devil and Daniel Webster -- Documents - 1955 -1959 -- Down East Suite -- Farm Journal -- Gallantry and the Boor (See Also Box 31) -- General Information About Works -- Giants in the Earth (Folders- l-2) -- Giants in the Earth Libretto (Ditto Sheets) -- Gook Night Poor Harvard -- Headless Horseman -- Lectures and California Trip - January 1950 (Box 16)
  - MacDowell Association, 1926 - 1928, ((Folders 1-2) ) (Box 17)
  - MacDowell Association, 1947 - 1959, ((Folders 1-2) ) (Box 17)
  - McGraw-Hill -- Mary's Player -- Memorian -- Miscellaneous Printed Material -- Music in the Making (Folders 1-2) -- Mysterious Cat -- National Institute of Arts and Letters - 1948-1960 (Folders 1-4) -- Old Song -- Overture on an American Tune (Box 17)
  - The Pageant of P.T. Barum -- Partch, Harry Oedipus -- Prayer for the United Nations -- Prentice Hall Correspondence - A-Z -- Printed Materials -- Programs and Advertisements -- Puss in Boots (Box 18)
  - Quartet 1933 -- Quintet for Winds -- References and Recommendations 1948 -1950 -- Society for Music in the Liberal Arts College -- Suite for Piano -- Symphony in A Major -- Vai-Choo-Loo -- Village Music -- White Wings -- Wings of the Dove -- Wonderful Violin -- Yale Alumni Council 1948 -1954 (Box 19)
- Series III: Columbia Course Material
  - Grades -- Student Papers -- Course Outlines, ((Binders 1-3) ) (Box 20)
  - "GS Music I" -- "Humanities" -- "Modern Music" -- "Music 107" -- "20th Century Music" (Box 21)
- Series IV: Scores
  Printed scores and a few books inscribed and signed by the following composers to D. S. Moore
  - Bacon, Ernst (Box 22 & 23)
  - Barnett, David (Box 22)
  - Binet, Jean (Box 22)
  - Bloch, Ernest (Box 22)
  - Carter, Elliott (Box 22)
  - Daniels, Mable (Box 22)
  - D'Indy, Vicent His cours de composition musicale, Paris, 1912 (Box 22)
    [With annotations in Moore's hand]
  - Dupre, Marcel (Box 22)
  - Helfer, Walter (Box 22)
  - Maganini, Quinto (Box 22)
  - Moore, Douglas, ((Folders 1-2) ) (Box 22)
  - Moore, Douglas (Box 23)
  - Myers, Richard (Box 23)
  - Parker, Horatio (Box 23)
  - Saminsky, L. (Box 23)
  - Sessions, Roger (Box 23)
  - Shepherd, Arthur (Box 23)
  - Spelman, Timothy Mather (Box 23)
  - Thompson, Randall (Box 23)
  - Trimble, Lester (Box 23)
  - Vasco, Mariz (Box 23)
  - Weisse, Hans (Box 23)
  - Winternitz, Emanuel (Box 23)
- Series V: Manuscripts Scores and Sketches in Moore's Hand
  Boxes 24 - 44
  - April Weather (Box 24)
  - Ballad of Baby Doe (Box 24)
  - Beethoven's Sonata Pathetique First Movement (Box 24)
  - Bird Song (Box 24)
  - Carry Nation (Box 24)
  - Cat Sat (Box 24)
  - Cello Sonata (Box 24)
  - Choral Varie (Box 24)
  - Class Song (Box 24)
  - Cleopatra's Mother (Box 24)
  - Copy Book (Box 24)
  - Cruise (Box 25)
  - Dear Dark Head (Box 25)
  - Dedication (Box 25)
  - Dedicatory Hymn (Box 25)
  - Destroyer Life (Folders ~-2) (Box 25)
  - Discouraged Churchill (Box 25)
  - Doughbcy S'eu, Fiche (Box 25)
  - Down at the North Fork Country Club Cabaret (Box 25)
  - Down East Suite (Box 25)
  - Early Song (Box 25)
  - Emperor's New Clothes (Folders 1-2) (Box 25)
  - Etude in Tenths (Box 25)
  - Fall of the City (Box 25)
  - Pantasie Polonaise (Box 25)
  - Film Music No. A (Box 25)
  - First Composition 1907 (Box 25)
  - Fourth Calvary- Regiment March (Box 25)
  - Friends, Elis Countrymen (Box 26)
  - Gallantry (See Also Box 31) (Box 26)
  - Giants of the Earth (Box 26)
  - Greek Games (Box 26)
  - Greenfield Christmas Tree (Box 26)
  - He's Gone Away (Box 26)
  - I Followed Lonely Down the Marne (Box 26)
  - In a Glass of,Water Before Retiring (Box 26)
  - In Springtime (Box 26)
  - Jesse James (Folders-1-3) (Box 26)
  - Jungle Heroes (Box 27)
  - Kimogenor (Box 27)
  - King Lear (Box 27)
  - Kitty-Cat Bird (Box 27)
  - Lja ne (Box 27)
  - Macleish Songs (Box 27)
  - Manuscript Notebook No. 8 (Box 27)
  - March (Box 27)
  - Martha (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous (Folders 1-3) (Box 27)
  - Moby Dick (Folders 1-9) (Box 28)
  - Movie Music -- Much Ado About Nothing -- My Garden -- Naomi -- North Atlantic Suite -- Notebook A-B -- Not this Alone -- Oh, Oh, Tennessee (Folders 1-2) (Box 29)
  - Oh, Oh, Tennessee -- Old Gray Mare -- Olympian Song -- Overture L'Atlan-Itique -- Overture Sketches -- Parabalou (Folders 1-2) -- Pelican Chorus -- Piano Scores -- Piano Sonata -- Poor Wayfaring Stranter (Box 30)
  - Power and the Land - Bass (Box 31)
  - Power and the Land - Cello (Box 31)
  - Power and the Land - Viola (Box 31)
  - Power and the Land - Violin (Yolders 1-4) (Box 31)
  - Power and the Land - Basson and Horn (Box 32)
  - Power and the Land - Clarinet (Box 32)
  - Power and the Land - Flute and Oboe (Box 32)
  - Power and the Land - Trumpet, Trombone, Percussion and Tympani (Box 32)
  - Power and the Land - Notes (Box 32)
  - Power and the Land - Rest of Score (Box 32)
  - Power and the Land - Suite (Box 32)
  - Prayer for England -- Prayer for U.N. (See also Flat Box) -- Puss in Boots -- Quartet Sketches -- Rural Electrification Film Parts 1-4 -- Rutgers Marching Song -- Snake Dance (Box 33)
  - Soldier Song -- Sonata for Piano and Violin 1-2 -- Sonata for Violincello -- Summer Evening 1-2 -- Symphony in A Major - Sketches -- Symphony of Autumn - Orchestral Score, a.ms.s (bound) 1980 Gift -- Symphony of Autumn - Parts Score, Setting copy in copyist's hand. 1980 Gift (Box 34)
  - Symphony of Autumn - Violin 1-7 (Box 35)
  - Symphony of Autumn - Viola 1-2 (Box 36)
  - Symphony of Autumn - Cello 1-2 (Box 36)
  - Symphony of Autumn - Bass (Box 36)
  - Tale of a Carp -- Then and Now -- Trio -- Trio for Violin, cello.and Piano, Score, a.ms. s. (See also Box 30) 1980 Gift -- Twelfth Night -- Twelfth Night and William Sycamore Sketche3 -- Valse Janet -- Variations for String Quartet -- White Wings 1-2 (Box 37)
  - White Wings - Choral Parts (mimeographed) 1-5 (Box 38)
  - White Wings - Choral Parts (mimeographed) .1-3 (Box 39)
  - White Wings - Choral Parts, (photocopy with handwritten annotations) (Box 40)
  - White Wings 1-3 -- William Sycamore -- Wings of the Dove -- Yale Pageant -- Yo Ho -- Young People Record (Box 41)
  - Youth get a Break - Manuscript Scores (Box 42)
- Series VI: Oversize Material
  - Devil and Daniel Webster, (Score and Sketches 1-2) (Box Flat Box 332)
  - Down East Suite, (Photocopy with handwritten Annotations) (Box Flat Box 333)
  - Devil and Daniel Webster -- Giants in the Earth -- Symphony, No. 2 in A Major - Two Pianos, Score, A.ms.s and 2 sets of blue prints -- Tamara M. Bliss - The Tyger Rit, excursion for oboe and piano, Come Away Death -- Trio for Violin, Cello and Piano, parts Score, 2 a.ms.s. (Violin and Cello only) -- Master cories and extracts -- White Wings and Simon Leg -- Kimogenor, A.ms. (fragment) score (Box Flat Box 333)
  - Greenfield Christmas Tree, (Score rolled up in a white folder) (Box Flat Box 336)
  - Gallantry as performed on CBS television program: Arias and Arabesques, Sept. 19, 1962, (Film, 2 reels ) (Box Flat Box 336)
    [NOT TO BE USED WITHOUT PERMISSION OF THE LIBRARIAN FOR RARE BOOKS & MANUSCRIPTS -- See related letters in Douglas Moore Office File.]
  - Babitt (Box Flat Box 334)
  - Prayer for the U.N. -- White Wings (Box Flat Box 335)